<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3031 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3031.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3985 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3985.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5921 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5921.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc8660 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8660.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std"
     docName="draft-ietf-detnet-tsn-vpn-over-mpls-03"
         ipr="trust200902"
         submissionType="IETF">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="TSN over DetNet MPLS">
    DetNet Data Plane: IEEE 802.1 Time Sensitive Networking over MPLS</title>

    <author role="editor" fullname="Bal&aacute;zs Varga" initials="B." surname="Varga">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Magyar Tudosok krt. 11.</street>
          <city>Budapest</city>
          <country>Hungary</country>
          <code>1117</code>
        </postal>
        <email>balazs.a.varga@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="J&aacute;nos Farkas" initials="J." surname="Farkas">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Magyar Tudosok krt. 11.</street>
          <city>Budapest</city>
          <country>Hungary</country>
          <code>1117</code>
        </postal>
        <email>janos.farkas@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Andrew G. Malis" initials="A.G." surname="Malis">
      <organization>Independent</organization>
      <address>
        <email>agmalis@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stewart Bryant" initials="S." surname="Bryant">
      <organization>Futurewei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
        <email>stewart.bryant@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Don Fedyk" initials="D." surname="Fedyk">
      <organization>LabN Consulting, L.L.C.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>dfedyk@labn.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

  <date />
  <workgroup>DetNet</workgroup>

  <abstract>
   <t>
     This document specifies the Deterministic Networking data plane
     when TSN networks are interconnected over a DetNet MPLS Network.
   </t>
  </abstract>
  </front>

 <middle>
 <section title="Introduction" anchor="sec_intro">
  <t>
        The Time-Sensitive Networking Task Group (TSN TG) within IEEE 802.1 Working 
        Group deals with deterministic services through IEEE 802 networks. 
    Deterministic Networking (DetNet) defined by IETF is a service that can be 
        offered by a L3 network to DetNet flows.  General background and concepts 
        of DetNet can be found in <xref target="RFC8655"/>.
  </t>
  <t>
        This document specifies the use of a DetNet MPLS network to interconnect TSN 
        nodes/network segments. DetNet MPLS data plane is defined in 
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-mpls"/>.
        <vspace blankLines="100" />   </t>
 </section>


 <section title="Terminology">
  <section title="Terms Used in This Document">
  <t>
        This document uses the terminology and concepts established in the DetNet 
        architecture <xref target="RFC8655"/> and 
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-data-plane-framework"/>, and 
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-mpls"/>.  The reader is assumed 
        to be familiar with these documents and their terminology.
  </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Abbreviations">
  <t>
   The following abbreviations are used in this document:
   <list style="hanging" hangIndent="14">
    <t hangText="AC">Attachment Circuit.</t>
    <t hangText="CE">Customer Edge equipment.</t>
    <t hangText="CW">Control Word.</t>
    <t hangText="DetNet">Deterministic Networking.</t>
    <t hangText="DF">DetNet Flow.</t>
    <t hangText="FRER">Frame Replication and Elimination for Redundancy 
        (TSN function).</t>
    <t hangText="L2">Layer 2.</t>
    <t hangText="L2VPN">Layer 2 Virtual Private Network.</t>
    <t hangText="L3">Layer 3.</t>
    <t hangText="LSR">Label Switching Router.</t>
    <t hangText="MPLS">Multiprotocol Label Switching.</t>
    <t hangText="MPLS-TE">Multiprotocol Label Switching - Traffic Engineering.</t>
    <t hangText="MPLS-TP">Multiprotocol Label Switching - Transport Profile.</t>
    <t hangText="NSP">Native Service Processing.</t>
    <t hangText="OAM">Operations, Administration, and Maintenance.</t>
    <t hangText="PE">Provider Edge.</t>
    <t hangText="PREOF">Packet Replication, Elimination and Ordering Functions.</t>
    <t hangText="PW">PseudoWire.</t>
    <t hangText="S-PE">Switching Provider Edge.</t>
    <t hangText="T-PE">Terminating Provider Edge.</t>
    <t hangText="TSN">Time-Sensitive Network.</t>
   </list>
  </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Requirements Language">
  <t>
    The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
    "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
    "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
    BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and
    only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
   </t>
   </section>
 </section>  <!-- end of terminology -->

<!-- =========================================== -->
<!--            TSN over DetNet MPLS             -->
<!-- =========================================== -->

<section title="IEEE 802.1 TSN Over DetNet MPLS Data Plane Scenario"
             anchor="sec_tsn_mpls_dt_dp_scen">

  <t>
   <xref target="fig_tsn_mpls_detnet"/> shows IEEE 802.1 TSN end
   stations operating over a TSN aware DetNet service running over an MPLS
   network.  DetNet Edge Nodes sit at the boundary of a DetNet domain. They are
   responsible for mapping non-DetNet aware L2 traffic to DetNet services.
   They also support the imposition and disposition of the required DetNet
   encapsulation.  These are functionally similar to pseudowire (PW)
   Terminating Provider Edge (T-PE) nodes which use MPLS-TE LSPs.  In this
   example TSN Streams are simple applicaions over DetNet flows.  The specific
   of this operation are discussed later in this document.
  </t>

<figure anchor="fig_tsn_mpls_detnet" align="center"
title="A TSN over DetNet MPLS Enabled Network">
<artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
   TSN           Edge          Transit         Edge          TSN
End System       Node           Node           Node       End System
                (T-PE)         (LSR)          (T-PE)

+----------+                                             +----------+
|   TSN    | <---------End to End TSN Service----------> |   TSN    |
|  Applic. |                                             |  Applic. |
+----------+  +.........+                   +.........+  +----------+
|          |  | \S-Proxy:                   :S-Proxy/ |  |          |
|   TSN    |  |   +.+---+<-- DetNet flow -->+---+ |   |  |   TSN    |
|          |  |TSN| |Svc|                   |Svc| |TSN|  |          |
+----------+  +---+ +---+    +----------+   +---+ +---+  +----------+
|   L2     |  | L2| |Fwd|    |Forwarding|   |Fwd| |L2 |  |   L2     |
+------.---+  +-.-+ +-.-+    +---.----.-+   +--.+ +-.-+  +---.------+
       :  Link  :     /  ,-----.  \   :  Link  :   /  ,-----. \
       +........+     +-[  Sub  ]-+   +........+   +-[  TSN  ]-+
                        [Network]                    [Network]
                         `-----'                      `-----'

                    |<------ DetNet MPLS ------>|
        |<---------------------- TSN   --------------------->|

]]></artwork>
</figure>

  <t>
        In this example, edge nodes provide a service proxy function that 
        "associates" the DetNet flows and native flows (i.e., TSN Streams) at
        the edge of the DetNet domain.  TSN streams are treated as App-flows 
		for DetNet. The whole DetNet domain behaves as a TSN relay node for 
		the TSN streams. The service proxy behaves as a port of that TSN 
		relay node. 
  </t>

  <t>
   <xref target="fig_8021_detnet"/> illustrates how DetNet can provide services 
   for IEEE 802.1 TSN end systems, CE1 and CE2, over a DetNet enabled MPLS 
   network.  Edge nodes, E1 and E2, insert and remove required DetNet data
   plane encapsulation.  The 'X' in the edge nodes and relay node, R1, 
   represent a potential DetNet compound flow  packet replication and 
   elimination point.  This conceptually parallels L2VPN services, and could
   leverage existing related solutions as discussed below.
  </t>

  <figure align="center" anchor="fig_8021_detnet"
  title="IEEE 802.1TSN Over DetNet">
  <artwork><![CDATA[
     TSN    |<------- End to End DetNet Service ------>|  TSN
    Service |         Transit          Transit         | Service
TSN  (AC)   |        |<-Tnl->|        |<-Tnl->|        |  (AC)  TSN
End    |    V        V    1  V        V   2   V        V   |    End
System |    +--------+       +--------+       +--------+   |  System
+---+  |    |   E1   |=======|   R1   |=======|   E2   |   |   +---+
|   |--|----|._X_....|..DF1..|.._ _...|..DF3..|...._X_.|---|---|   |
|CE1|  |    |    \   |       |   X    |       |   /    |   |   |CE2|
|   |       |     \_.|..DF2..|._/ \_..|..DF4..|._/     |       |   |
+---+       |        |=======|        |=======|        |       +---+
    ^       +--------+       +--------+       +--------+       ^
    |        Edge Node       Relay Node        Edge Node       |
    |          (T-PE)           (S-PE)          (T-PE)         |
    |                                                          |
    |<- TSN -> <------- TSN Over DetNet MPLS -------> <- TSN ->|
    |                                                          |
    |<-------- Time Sensitive Networking (TSN) Service ------->|

    X   = Service protection
    DFx = DetNet member flow x over a TE LSP
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>

  </section>

<!-- ================================================= -->
<!--            DetNet MPLS data plane OVERVIEW        -->
<!-- ================================================= -->

 <section title="DetNet MPLS Data Plane" anchor="sec_dt_dp">

 <section title="Overview" anchor="sec_dt_dp_ov">
 <t>
        The basic approach defined in <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-mpls"/>
        supports the DetNet service sub-layer based on existing pseudowire (PW) 
        encapsulations and mechanisms, and supports the DetNet forwarding 
        sub-layer based on existing MPLS Traffic Engineering encapsulations 
        and mechanisms. 
 </t>
 <t>
        A node operating on a DetNet flow in the Detnet service sub-layer, i.e. 
        a node processing a DetNet packet which has the S-Label as top of stack 
        uses the local context associated with that S-Label, for example a received 
        F-Label, to determine what local DetNet operation(s) are applied to that 
        packet. An S-Label may be unique when taken from the platform
        label space <xref target="RFC3031"/>, which would enable correct DetNet flow
        identification regardless of which input interface or LSP the packet arrives 
        on. The service sub-layer functions (i.e., PREOF) use a DetNet control word 
        (d-CW).
 </t>
 <t>
    The DetNet MPLS data plane builds on MPLS Traffic Engineering
    encapsulations and mechanisms to provide a forwarding sub-layer that
    is responsible for providing resource allocation and explicit
    routes.  The forwarding sub-layer is supported by one or more
    forwarding labels (F-Labels).
 </t>
 <t>
        DetNet edge/relay nodes are DetNet service sub-layer
        aware, understand the particular needs of DetNet flows and
        provide both DetNet service and forwarding sub-layer functions.
        They add, remove and process d-CWs, S-Labels and F-labels as
        needed.  MPLS enabled DetNet nodes can enhance the
        reliability of delivery by enabling the replication of packets
        where multiple copies, possibly over multiple paths, are
        forwarded through the DetNet domain.  They can also eliminate
        surplus previously replicated copies of DetNet packets.
        MPLS (DetNet) nodes also include
        DetNet forwarding sub-layer functions, support for notably
        explicit routes, and resources allocation to eliminate (or
        reduce) congestion loss and jitter.
 </t>
 <t>
        DetNet transit nodes reside wholly within a DetNet domain, and
        also provide DetNet forwarding sub-layer functions in accordance
        with the performance required by a DetNet flow carried over an
        LSP. Unlike other DetNet node types, transit nodes provide no
        service sub-layer processing.
 </t>
 </section>

 <section anchor="tom-encap"
               title="TSN over DetNet MPLS Encapsulation">
 <t>
        The basic encapsulation approach is to treat a TSN Stream as an app-flow 
        from the DetNet MPLS perspective. The corresponding example shown in 
        <xref target="fig_tsn_mpls_ex"/>.
 </t>

  <figure title="Example TSN over MPLS Encapsulation Formats"
              anchor="fig_tsn_mpls_ex">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

           /->     +------+  +------+  +------+   TSN      ^ ^
           |       |  X   |  |  X   |  |  X   |<- Appli    : :
App-Flow <-+       +------+  +------+  +------+   cation   : :(1)
 for MPLS  |       |TSN-L2|  |TSN-L2|  |TSN-L2|            : v
           \-> +---+======+--+======+--+======+-----+      :
                   | d-CW |  | d-CW |  | d-CW |            :
DetNet-MPLS        +------+  +------+  +------+            :(2)
                   |Labels|  |Labels|  |Labels|            v
               +---+======+--+======+--+======+-----+
Link/Sub-Network   |  L2  |  | TSN  |  | UDP  |
                   +------+  +------+  +------+
                                       |  IP  |
                                       +------+
                                       |  L2  |
                                       +------+
    (1) TSN Stream 
    (2) DetNet MPLS Flow
    ]]>
        </artwork>
  </figure>

 <t>
        In the figure, "Application" indicates the application payload carried by 
        the TSN network. "MPLS App-Flow" indicates that the TSN Stream is the 
        payload from the perspective of the DetNet MPLS data plane defined in 
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-mpls"/>. A single DetNet MPLS flow 
        can aggregate multiple TSN Streams.
 </t>
 </section>

 </section>  <!-- end of DetNet MPLS data plane overview -->

<!-- ================================================= -->
<!--            TSN over DetNet MPLS procedures        -->
<!-- ================================================= -->

 <section title="TSN over MPLS Data Plane Procedures" anchor="tom_proc">

  <t>
        Description of Edge Nodes procedures and functions for TSN over DetNet MPLS
        scenario follows the concept of <xref target="RFC3985"/> and covers the 
        Edge Nodes components shown on <xref target="fig_tsn_mpls_detnet"/>. In 
        this section the following procedures of DetNet Edge Nodes are described:
        <list style="symbols">
                <t>
                        TSN related (<xref target="tom_tsn_proc"/>)
                </t><t>
                        DetNet Service Proxy (<xref target="tom_svc_prx_proc"/>)
                </t><t>
                        DetNet service and forwarding sub-layer (<xref target="tom_dn_sub_proc"/>)
                </t>
        </list>
  </t>
  <t>  
		The sub-sections describe procedures for forwarding packets by DetNet 
		Edge nodes, where such packets are received from either directly 
		connected CEs (TSN nodes) or some other DetNet Edge nodes.
  </t>
  

  <section title="Edge Node TSN Procedures" anchor="tom_tsn_proc">
    <t>
        The Time-Sensitive Networking (TSN) Task Group of the IEEE 802.1 
                Working Group have defined (and are defining) a number of amendments 
                to <xref target="IEEE8021Q">IEEE 802.1Q</xref> that provide zero 
                congestion loss and bounded latency in bridged networks.
        <xref target="IEEE8021CB">IEEE 802.1CB</xref> defines packet 
                replication and elimination functions for a TSN network.
          </t>
          <t>
                TSN specific functions are executed on the data received by 
                the DetNet Edge Node from the connected CE before forwarded to 
				connected CE(s) or presentation to the DetNet Service Proxy function for 
                transmission across the DetNet domain, or on the data received from 
                a DetNet PW by a PE before it is output on the Attachment Circuit(s) (AC). 
          </t>
          <t>
                TSN specific function(s) of Edge Nodes (T-PE) are belonging to the 
                native service processing (NSP) <xref target="RFC3985"/> 
                block. This is similar to other functionalities being defined by standard 
                bodies other than the IETF (for example in case of Ethernet: stripping, 
                overwriting or adding VLAN tags, etc.). Depending on the TSN role of 
                the Edge Node in the end-to-end TSN service selected TSN functions 
                must be supported. 
    </t>
    <t>		
			When a PE receives a packet from a CE, on a given AC with DetNet service,
			it MUST first check via Stream Identification whether the packet belongs 
			to a configured TSN Stream (i.e., App-flow from DetNet perspective). 
			If no Stream ID is matched and no other (VPN) service is configured 
			for the AC then packet MUST be dropped. If there is a matching TSN 
			Stream then the Stream-ID specific TSN functions MUST be executed 
			(e.g., ingress policing, header field manipulation in case 
			of active Stream Identification, FRER, etc.). Source MAC lookup 
			MAY also be used for local MAC address learning.
    </t>
    <t>		
			If the PE decides to forward the packet, the packet MUST be forwarded 
			according to the TSN Stream specific configuration to connected CE(s) 
			(in case of local bridging) and/or to the DetNet Service Proxy 
			(in case of forwarding to remote CE(s) required). If there are no 
			TSN Stream specific forwarding configurations the PE MUST flood 
			the packet to other locally attached CE(s) and to the DetNet Service 
			Proxy. If the administrative policy on the PE does not allow 
			flooding the PE MUST drop the packet.
    </t>
    <t>		
			When a TSN entity of the PE receives a packet from the DetNet 
			Service Proxy, it MUST first check via Stream Identification whether 
			the packet belongs to a configured TSN Stream. If no Stream ID is 
			matched then packet MUST be dropped. If there is a matching TSN 
			Stream then the Stream ID specific TSN functions MUST be executed 
			(e.g., header field manipulation in case of active Stream 
			Identification, FRER, etc.). Source MAC lookup MAY also be used for 
			local MAC address learning.
    </t>
    <t>		
			If the PE decides to forward the packet, the packet MUST be forwarded 
			according to the TSN Stream specific configuration to connected CE(s).
			If there are no TSN Stream specific forwarding configurations the 
			PE MUST flood the packet to locally attached CE(s). If the 
			administrative policy on the PE does not allow flooding the PE MUST 
			drop the packet.
    </t>
    <t>
                Implementations of this document SHALL use management and
                control information to ensure TSN specific functions of the Edge Node
                according to the expectations of the connected TSN network. 
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Edge Node DetNet Service Proxy Procedures" anchor="tom_svc_prx_proc">
          <t>
                The Service Proxy
                function maps between App-flows and DetNet flows.
				The DetNet Edge Node TSN entity MUST support the TSN Stream
                identification functions and the related managed objects as
                defined in <xref target="IEEE8021CB">IEEE 802.1CB</xref> and
                <xref target="IEEEP8021CBdb">IEEE P802.1CBdb</xref> to
                recognize the App-flow related packets.  The Service Proxy
                presents TSN Streams as an App-flow to a DetNet Flow.
		  </t>
		<t>		
			When a DetNet Service Proxy receives a packet from the TSN Entity
			it MUST check whether such an App-flow is present in its mapping table.
			If present it associates the internal DetNet flow-ID to the packet and 
			MUST forward it to the DetNet Service and Forwarding sub-layers. If 
			no matching statement is present it MUST drop the packet.
		</t>
		<t>		
			When a DetNet Service Proxy receives a packet from the DetNet Service 
			and Forwarding sub-layers it MUST be forwarded to the Edge Node 
			TSN Entity. 
		</t>
		  <t>
                Implementations of this document SHALL use management and
                control information to map a TSN Stream to a DetNet flow. 
                N:1 mapping (aggregating multiple TSN Streams in a single
                DetNet flow) SHALL be supported. The management or control
                function that provisions flow mapping SHALL ensure that
                adequate resources are allocated and configured to provide
                proper service requirements of the mapped flows.
        </t>
        <t>
                Due to the (intentional) similarities of the DetNet PREOF and
                TSN FRER functions service protection function interworking is
                possible between the TSN and the DetNet domains. Such service
                protection interworking scenarios MAY require to copy sequence
                number fields from TSN (L2) to PW (MPLS) encapsulation.
                However, such interworking is out-of-scope in this document and
                left for further study.
        </t>
        <t>
                A MPLS DetNet flow is configured to carry any number of
                TSN flows. The DetNet flow specific bandwidth profile SHOULD 
				match the required bandwidth of the App-flow aggregate.  
        </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Edge Node DetNet Service and Forwarding Sub-Layer Procedures" anchor="tom_dn_sub_proc">
          <t>
                In the design of <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-mpls"/> an MPLS service 
                label (the S-Label), similar to a pseudowire (PW) label 
                <xref target="RFC3985"/>, is used to identify both the DetNet flow 
                identity and the payload MPLS payload type.  The DetNet sequence 
                number is carried in the DetNet Control word (d-CW) which carries the 
                Data/OAM discriminator as well. In 
                <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-mpls"/> two sequence number sizes 
                are supported: a 16 bit sequence number and a 28 bit sequence number.
    </t>
    <t>
                PREOF functions and the provided service recovery is available
                only within the DetNet domain as the DetNet flow-ID and the DetNet
                sequence number are not valid outside the DetNet network.  MPLS
                (DetNet) Edge node terminates all related information elements 
                encoded in the MPLS labels.
        </t>
        <t>
                The LSP used to forward the DetNet packet may be of any type (MPLS-LDP, 
                MPLS-TE, MPLS-TP <xref target="RFC5921"/>, or MPLS-SR 
                <xref target="RFC8660"/>).  The LSP 
                (F-Label) label and/or the S-Label may be used to indicate the queue 
                processing as well as the forwarding parameters.
        </t>
    <t>		
			When a PE receives a packet from the Service Proxy function it MUST
			add to the packet the DetNet flow-ID specific S-label and create a 
			d-CW. The PE MUST forward the packet according to the configured 
			DetNet Service and Forwarding sub-layer rules to other PE nodes. 
    </t>
    <t>		
			When a PE receives an MPLS packet from a remote PE, then, after 
			processing the MPLS label stack, if the top MPLS label ends up being 
			a DetNet S-label that was advertised by this node, then the PE 
			MUST forward the packet according to the configured DetNet Service and 
			Forwarding sub-layer rules to other PE nodes or via the Detnet Service 
			Proxy function towards locally connected CE(s). 
    </t>
    <t>
                For further details on DetNet Service and Forwarding sub-layers 
				see <xref target="I-D.ietf-detnet-mpls"/>.
        </t>
  </section>

 </section>  <!-- End of Procedures Section -->


<!-- ========================================================== -->
<!--          Management and Control Plane Considerations       -->
<!-- ========================================================== -->

 <section title="Controller Plane (Management and Control) Considerations" anchor="cp_considerations">

   <t>
        TSN Stream(s) to DetNet flow mapping related information are
        required only for the service proxy function of MPLS (DetNet) Edge nodes. 
        From the Data Plane perspective there is no practical difference
		based on the origin of flow mapping related information	(management 
		plane or control plane).
   </t>
   <t>
        MPLS DetNet Edge nodes are member of both the DetNet domain and the
        connected TSN network. From the TSN network perspective the MPLS
        (DetNet) Edge node has a "TSN relay node" role, so TSN specific
        management and control plane functionalities must be implemented.
        There are many similarities in the management plane techniques used in
        DetNet and TSN, but that is not the case for the control plane
        protocols. For example, RSVP-TE and MSRP behaves differently.  
		Therefore management and control plane design is an important aspect 
		of scenarios, where	mapping between DetNet and TSN is required.
   </t>
   <t>
        Note that, as the DetNet network is just a portion of the end to end TSN
        path (i.e., single hop from Ethernet perspective), some parameters
        (e.g., delay) may differ significantly.  Since there is no interworking
        function the bandwidth of DetNet network is assumed to be set large enough to
        handle all TSN Flows it will support.  At the egress of the Detnet Domain the MPLS
        headers are stripped and the TSN flow continues on as a normal TSN
        flow. 
	</t>
	<t>
        In order to use a DetNet network to interconnect TSN segments,
        TSN specific information must be converted to DetNet domain
        specific ones. TSN Stream ID(s) and stream(s) related
        parameters/requirements must be converted to a DetNet flow-ID and 
        flow related parameters/requirements.
   </t>
   <t>
        In some case it may be challenging to determine some egress node
        related information. For example, it may be not trivial to
        locate the egress point/interface of a TSN Streams with a 
        multicast destination MAC address. Such scenarios may
        require interaction between control and management plane
        functions and between DetNet and TSN domains.
   </t>
   <t>
        Mapping between DetNet flow identifiers and TSN Stream
        identifiers, if not provided explicitly, can be done by the service
        proxy function of an MPLS (DetNet) Edge node locally based on information
        provided for configuration of the TSN Stream identification functions 
        (e.g., Mask-and-Match Stream identification).
   </t>
   <t>
        Triggering the setup/modification of a DetNet flow in the
        DetNet network is an example where management and/or
        control plane interactions are required between the DetNet
        and the TSN network. 
   </t>
   <t>
        Configuration of TSN specific functions (e.g., FRER)
        inside the TSN network is a TSN domain specific decision 
        and may not be visible in the DetNet domain. Service protection
        interworking scenarios are left for further study.
   </t>
</section> <!-- End of Management and Control Plane COnsiderations -->

<section title="Security Considerations">
  <t>
     Security considerations for DetNet are described in detail in <xref
             target="I-D.ietf-detnet-security"/>. General security
     considerations are described in <xref
             target="RFC8655"/>.  DetNet MPLS data plane
     specific considerations are summarized in <xref
             target="I-D.ietf-detnet-mpls"/>.  
     
     The primary considerations for
     the data plane is to maintain integrity of data and delivery of the
     associated DetNet service traversing the DetNet network.  Application
     flows can be protected through whatever means is provided by the
     underlying technology. For example, encryption may be used, such as that
     provided by IPSec <xref target="RFC4301"/> for IP flows and/or by an
     underlying sub-net using MACSec <xref target="IEEE802.1AE-2018"/> for IP
     over Ethernet (Layer-2) flows. 
    </t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
  <t>
   This document makes no IANA requests.
  </t>
</section>

<section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgements">
   <t>
                The authors wish to thank Norman Finn, Lou Berger, Craig Gunther,
                Christophe Mangin and Jouni Korhonen for their various contributions 
                to this work.
   </t>
</section>
</middle>

<back>
  <references title="Normative References">
   &rfc2119;
   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3031"?>
   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
   <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-detnet-mpls"?>
  </references>
  <references title="Informative References">
   &rfc3985;
   &rfc5921;
   &rfc8660;
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8655"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-detnet-data-plane-framework"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-detnet-security"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4301"?>


    <reference anchor="IEEE802.1AE-2018"
      target="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/8585421">
      <front>
        <title>IEEE Std 802.1AE-2018 MAC Security (MACsec)</title>
        <author>
          <organization>IEEE Standards Association</organization>
        </author>
        <date year="2018" />
      </front>
    </reference>

   <reference anchor="IEEE8021Q"
     target="http://standards.ieee.org/about/get/">
    <front>
     <title>Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks--Bridges and Bridged Networks (IEEE Std 802.1Q-2014)</title>
     <author>
      <organization>IEEE 802.1</organization>
     </author>
     <date year="2014"/>
    </front>
    <format type="PDF" target="http://standards.ieee.org/about/get/"/>
   </reference>

   <reference anchor="IEEE8021CB"
    target="http://www.ieee802.org/1/files/private/cb-drafts/d2/802-1CB-d2-1.pdf">
    <front>
        <title>Draft Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks - Seamless Redundancy</title>
        <author initials="N. F." surname="Finn" fullname="Norman Finn">
            <organization>IEEE 802.1</organization>
        </author>
        <date month="December" year="2015"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="IEEE P802.1CB /D2.1" value="P802.1CB"/>
    <format type="PDF" target="http://www.ieee802.org/1/files/private/cb-drafts/d2/802-1CB-d2-1.pdf"/>
   </reference>

      <reference anchor="IEEEP8021CBdb"
                 target="http://www.ieee802.org/1/files/private/cb-drafts/d2/802-1CB-d2-1.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Extended Stream identification functions</title>
          <author initials="C. M." surname="Mangin" fullname="Christophe Mangin">
            <organization>IEEE 802.1</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="August" year="2019"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="IEEE P802.1CBdb /D0.2" value="P802.1CBdb"/>
        <format type="PDF" target="http://www.ieee802.org/1/files/private/cb-drafts/d2/802-1CB-d2-1.pdf"/>
      </reference>


  </references>

 </back>
</rfc>
